Jonathan Trumbull, Jr. Papers
Connecticut Historical Society
Jonathan Trumbull, Jr. Papers.
1753-1832
Connecticut Historical Society
Jonathan Trumbull, Jr.
Collection consists of Jonathan Trumbull, Jr.'s personal and professional correspondence, militia papers, financial records, and some documents relating to specified fugitives.
3.5 linear feet (4 boxes)
Related Material
An index of catalog cards is available to aid access to this collection and material in other collections. Access is through writer, recipient and date. The card catalog is located in the Research Center reading room.
Microfilm copy available.
Biographical Sketch
Jonathan Trumbull, Jr. was born on March 26, 1740 in Lebanon, Connecticut, the eldest son of Jonathan and Faith (Robinson) Trumbull. He received his early education from Nathan Tisdale and at the age of fifteen commenced studies at Harvard College. He was the salutatorian for his class in 1759, and three years later delivered the valedictory address when he obtained his M.A.
Following graduation, Trumbull returned to his native Lebanon, Connecticut, where he confined his business to a small store and thereby avoided the financial woes that would plague the trading interests of his father and brother. In 1769, he married Eunice Backus, daughter of Ebenezer and Eunice (Dyer) Backus of Norwich, Connecticut. Together they had one son and four daughters.
Trumbull's long political life began in 1770, when he was elected to the Lebanon Board of Selectmen. Five years later, in March 1775, he was elected to sit in the Connecticut General Assembly. While still in that position, the Continental Congress elected him "pay master of the forces for the New York department," with the rank of colonel. Following this was his November 3, 1778 election to be the first comptroller of the U.S. Treasury. His public duties became even more illustrious when on June 8, 1781 he was appointed to succeed Alexander Hamilton as George Washington's secretary. His military duties ended with Washington's resignation in 1784, and at this time he returned to Connecticut where in 1788 he once again sat in the General Assembly, this time as Speaker.
Trumbull left his home state once again in 1789, upon his election to the House of Representatives, where he served from 1789-1795 (and as Speaker of the House from 1791-1794). He advanced to the Senate in 1795, but resigned in 1796 to return to Connecticut. There, he served as Lieutenant Governor under Oliver Wolcott, and in 1797 he became Governor upon Wolcott's death. Still serving as Governor, he became embroiled in a political crisis in 1809 over the Embargo Act. James Madison ordered that the State militia be called out to enforce the Embargo. Trumbull (with the support of many of the state's residents) refused to comply. Later that year his time as governor ended with his death from "dropsy of the heart" on August 7, 1809.
Scope and Content
Collection consists largely of correspondence written in both personal and official roles. Such correspondence is arranged chronologically. Also numerous are militia records, including several folders of court martial documents and militia returns. Third in quantity are receipts, accounts, and bills, most of which stem from Trumbull's time as Paymaster. Of special interest are papers relating to Jonathan Trumbull, Jr.'s estate, including his Last Will and Testament, as well as records from the votes of Connecticut towns on the controversial Embargo of 1809. Some notable correspondents include Eliphalet Dyer, William Williams, Oliver Wolcott, Henry Knox, John Pierce, James Madison, John Hancock, and Timothy Dwight.
Arrangement
Materials are organized into three series based largely on form.
Series I: Correspondence consists of correspondence, both professional and personal. Much of it comes from Trumbull's time as Paymaster and from his time in Congress.
Series II: Militia Papers consists of court martials and militia returns.
Series III: Receipts, Accounts, and Bills consists of receipts, accounts, and bills, most of which were created during Trumbull's time as Paymaster for the New York forces and Comptroller for the U.S. Treasury.
Collection is arranged chronologically within in each series.
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions on access to the collection.
Accruals
The collection is open, but additional material is not expected.
Subject Headings
Personal Names
Dwight, Timothy, 1752-1817.; Dyer, Eliphalet, 1721-1807.; Goodrich, Chauncey, 1759-1815.; Hancock, John, 1737-1793.; Hillhouse, James, 1754-1832.; Knox, Henry.; Livingston, Henry Brockholst, 1757-1823.; Madison, James, 1751-1836.; Pierce, John.; Schuyler, Philip John, 1733-1804.; Trumbull, John, 1756-1843.; Trumbull, Jonathan, 1710-1785.; Trumbull, Joseph, 1737-1778.; Williams, William, 1731-1811.; Wolcott, Oliver, 1726-1797.; Wolcott, Oliver, 1760-1833.
Corporate Names
Connecticut Militia.
Subjects
Courts-martial and courts of inquiry.; Embargo, 1807-1809.; Fugitives from justice.
Geographic Names
United States History Revolution Sources.; United States Politics and government 1789-1797.; Connecticut Politics and government 1775-1865.
Genre Forms
Holographs; holographs, signed.
Contents:
- I. Correspondence
  - Correspondence with Congressmen, including E[liphalet] Dyer, Jonathan Trumbull, Jr., William Williams, and Jeremiah Wadsworth., 1780-1796 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - U.S. Government letters; correspondence to and from such men as Geo[rge] Bond, Robert Morris, and Oliver Wolcott., 1776-1793 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - U.S. Government letters from Henry Knox., 1793 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - U.S. Government letters; correspondence to and from such men as Henry Knox, Alexander Hamilton, Oliver Wolcott, Sam Otis, and Timothy Pickering., 1794-1797 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - U.S. Government letters; correspondence to and from such men as Jonathan Trumbull, Jr., Timothy Pickering, J. Huntington, and William Lambert., 1797-1799 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - U.S. Government letters; correspondence to and from such men as Jonathan Trumbull, Jr., James Henry, Timothy Pickering, and John Porter., 1799-1800 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - U.S. Government letters; correspondence to and from such men as Jonathan Trumbull, Jr., Jacob Wagner, James Madison, and Sam Otis., 1800-1803 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - U.S. Government letters; correspondence to and from such men as James Madison, Jonathan Trumbull, Jr., and J[acob] Wagner., 1804-1809 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence from Jonathan Trumbull's term as Paymaster of the forces for the New York department, including letters to and from Elisha Phelps, Alexander McDougall, John Winslow, Jed Huntington, Roger Sherman, and David Trumbull., 1775-1776 (Volume 2)
  - Correspondence from Jonathan Trumbull's term as Paymaster of the forces for the New York department and Comptroller of the U.S. treasury, including letters to and from Charles Thompson, John Winslow, Jonathan Trumbull, Sr., David Trumbull, John Pierce, Roger Sherman, and Sam Huntington., 1776-1783 (Volume 3)
  - Correspondence -- mostly from Trumbull's time as a Congressmen -- including letters to and from Jeremiah Wadsworth, William Williams, Chauncey Goodrich, James Hillhouse, and Uriah Fray., 1780-1801 (Volume 4)
  - Correspondence with Congressmen, including letters to and from Uriah Fray, James Hillhouse, Simeon Baldwin, C. Goddard, and Benjamin Tallmadge., 1801-1818 (Volume 5)
  - Correspondence with such men as Benjamin Butler, Christopher Leffingwell, John Lane, David Trumbull, John Hancock, and Horatio Gates., 1756-1777 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence with such men as Charles Thomson, Timothy Pickering, and Joseph Loomis., 1778-1783 (Box 6, Folder 2)
    Note: Transcript available
  - Correspondence with such men as Isaac Winslow, Roger Alden, Benjamin Huntington, and Andrew Billings., 1784-1788 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence with such men as David Trumbull, George Phillips, Jabez Huntington, and William Williams., 1789-1795 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence with such men as William Williams, Richard Saltonstall, Timothy Pickering, and Frederick Wolcott., 1796-1797 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence with such men as Frederick Wolcott, Benjamin Trumbull, Guy Richards, and Jabez Huntington., January-July 1798 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence with such men as Samuel Huntington, Daniel Jones, and John Smalley., August-December 1798 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence with such men as Jabez Huntington, Timothy Dwight, Samuel Dana, and Timothy Phelps., January-July 1799 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence with such men as Benjamin Trumbull, John Allen, and Samuel Wyllys., August-December 1799 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence with such men as Jesse Rook, John Porter, John Jay, Timothy Dwight, and Philip Bradley., January-April 1800 (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence with such men as Joseph Isham, William Tully, James Monroe, Jesse Rook, Andrew Huntington, and Elisha Hale., May-September 1800 (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence with such men as Elizur Goodrich, William Tully, John Mix, and George Cabot., October-December 1800 (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence relating to the case of fugitive Gould Linell., February-July 1800 (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence with such men as Joseph Wilcox, Timothy Dwight, Timothy Crane, Elijah Chapman, and Elizur Goodrich., January-June 1801 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence with such men as Joseph Willcox (sic), George Morgan, William Edmond, John Walden, and Jabez Clark., July-December 1801 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence with such men as William Woodbridge, Abraham Jarvis, and Henry Seymour., January-August 1802 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence with such men as Joshua King, John Mix, Stephen Brown, and Andrew Huntington., September-December 1802 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence with such men as John Porter, Justus Barnum, Eli Mather, Henry Seymour, Peter Whitney, and Samuel Williams., January-June 1803 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence with such men as John Porter, Elias Perkins, John Felch, and Simeon Baldwin., July-December 1803 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence with such men as Justus Barnum, John Porter, Daniel Winship, David Humphreys, and William Edmond., January-July 1804 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence with such men as Elijah Parsons, William Seymour, Uriah Tracy, and James Madison., August-December 1804 (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence with such men as Andrew Hull, Ebenezer Huntington, John Porter, Frederick Wolcott, and Jeremiah Guild., 1805 (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence with such men as Thomas Sanford, Charles Thompson, William Cogswell, Nathan Perkins, Jed Huntington, and James Mason., 1806 (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence with such men as Seth Smith, Michael Abott, and Joshua Huntington., January-July 1807 (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence with such men as John Elliott, E.S. Thomas, and Ebenezer Huntington., August-December 1807 (Box 7, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence with such men as George Elliott, William Pinchney, Roswell Colt, Matthew Griswold, and Jesse Brown., 1808 (Box 7, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence with such men as George Cabot, Josiah Griffin, and Ebenezer Huntington; and an account of Jonathan Trumbull, Jr.'s death, probably written by his son-in-law, Daniel Wadsworth., 1809 (Box 7, Folder 14)
  - Correspondence with such men as Grenville Temple and William Williams., 1756-1809 (Box 7, Folder 15)
  - Correspondence regarding fugitive Israel Stone., January 1797-December 1798 (Box 7, Folder 16)
  - Correspondence regarding fugitive Robert Rogers., May-June 1798 (Box 7, Folder 17)
  - Correspondence regarding the separate cases of fugitives Noah Agard, Anna Bishop, and John S. Green., October 1798-December 1799 (Box 7, Folder 18)
  - Correspondence regarding fugitive Abram Frost., August 1800 (Box 7, Folder 19)
  - Correspondence regarding the separate cases of fugitives Joseph Brown and Elisha Rose., December 1805; January-May 1807 (Box 7, Folder 20)
- II. Militia papers
  - Militia papers: court martials., May 1798-January 1802 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Militia papers: court martials., May 1802 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Militia papers: court martials., November 1802-March 1803 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Militia papers: court martials., May 1803 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Militia papers: court martials., June 1803-October 1804 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Militia papers: court martials., November 1804 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Militia papers: court martials., January 1805-June 1806 (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Militia papers: court martials., July-November 1807 (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - Militia papers: court martials., 1808 (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - Militia papers: court martials., January-March 1809 (Box 8, Folder 10)
  - Militia papers: court martials., April 1809 (Box 8, Folder 11)
  - Militia papers: militia returns., 1795-1797 (Box 8, Folder 12)
  - Militia papers: militia returns., 1798-1799 (Box 8, Folder 13)
  - Militia papers: militia returns., 1800-1801 (Box 8, Folder 14)
  - Militia papers: militia returns., 1802-1803 (Box 8, Folder 15)
  - Militia papers: militia returns., 1804 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Militia papers: militia returns., 1805-1806 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Militia papers: militia returns., 1807 (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Militia papers: militia returns., 1808 (Box 9, Folder 4)
- III. Receipts, Accounts, and Bills
  - Receipts, accounts, bills: Paymaster General letter book, 1775-1778 (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Receipts, accounts, bills: Paymaster General letter book, 1779-1780 (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - Receipts, accounts, bills: Paymaster General, 1776 (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - Receipts, accounts, bills: Paymaster General, 1776 (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - Receipts, accounts, bills: Paymaster General, 1777 (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - Receipts, accounts, bills: Paymaster General, 1775-1784 (Box 9, Folder 10)
  - Receipts, accounts, bills: personal business papers, 1753-1805 (Box 9, Folder 11)
  - Receipts, accounts, bills: account sheets of Jonathan and David Trumbull, 1780-1785 (Box 9, Folder 12)
  - Receipts, accounts, bills: votes on the embargo, from towns including Hampton, New Haven, Derby, and Canterbury, 1809 (Box 9, Folder 13)
  - Receipts, accounts, bills: documents relating to the personal estate of Jonathan Trumbull, Jr., including his Last Will and Testament, 1808-1832 (Box 9, Folder 14)